在这部分，我们会继续了解一些其他的离散概率的工具
In this segment, we're gonna continue with
a few more tools from discrete
我想提醒大家如果你们想在维基百科中
probability, and I want to remind everyone
that if you wanna read more about this,
了解更多关于这个工具,那么链接在这里。所以首先
there's more information in wiki books
article that is linked over here. So first
让我们快速回顾一下之前学到了哪里。我们说离散概率
let's do a quick recap of where we are. We
said that the discrete probability is
总是定义在一个有限的集合上，我们用U来表示，通常表示为这些，
always defined over a finite set, which
we're gonna denote by U, and typically for
U将成为所有N位的设置二进制字符串，指示为01N
us, U is going to be the set of all N bit
binary strings, which we denote by zero
现在的一个概率分布P在这个集合U上基本上是一个
130 N. Now a probability distribution P
over this universe U is basically a
函数，指定在区域[0,1]区间内的每一个元素，
function that assigns to every element in
the universe a weight in the interval zero
这样如果我们将所有这些元素的权重求和，会发现和就会等于一
to one, such that if we sum the weight of
all these elements, the sum basically sums
现在我们说，集合的子集是什么被称为一个事件，
up to one. Now we have said that subset of
the universe is what called an event, and
一个事件的概率是事件中所有元素权重的总和，
we said that probability of an event is
basically the sum of all the weights of
我们说，事件的概率是在
all the elements in the event and we said
that probability of an event is some real
零到一之间的实数，并且还有一点
numbers in the interval zero to one And I
would remind everyone the basically
整个集合概率一定是所有的权重和，并且等于一。
probability of the entire universe is
basically the one by the fact that sum of
然后我们定义一个正式的随机变量
all the weights sums up to one. Then we
define what a random variable is Formally,
这个随机变量是一个来自其他集合来的函数
a random variable is a, is a function from
the universe of some other sets But the
但你要记住的是，这些随机变量在集合V中所代表的含义
thing that I want you to remember is that
the random variable takes, values in some
事实上，随机变量的分布定义了这个集合V。
set v And, in fact, the random variable
defines the distribution on this set v. So
所以我们需要学习的下一个概念是什么叫做独立性，我会非常简要的定义它，
the next concept we need is what's called
independence And I'm gonna very briefly
如果你想了解更多关于独立性的内容，请去看看维基百科
define this If you want to read more about
independence, please go ahead and look at
但本质上我们说A和B这两个事件是
the wiki books article. But essentially we
say that two events A and B are
彼此独立的，如果你知道当事件A发生时，
independent of one another if When you
know that event A happens, that tells you
你不知道事件B是否发生。形式上，
nothing about whether event B actually
happened or not. Formally, the way we
我们定义独立性就是说，A和B同时发生的概率
define independence is to say that, the
probability of A and B, namely, that both
就等于事件A的概率和事件B的概率的乘积
events happened, is actually=to the
probability of event A the probability of
从某种意义上说，只要符合这一事实
event B So mult iplication, in some sense,
the fact that probabilities multiply under
这些事件就是独立的。就像我之前说的那样，
conjunction, captures the fact that these
events are independent And as I said, if
如果你想了解更多，请看背景材料。
you wanna read more about that, please
take a look at the background material.
现在同样的理论可以应用在随机变量上。假如我们有两个随机
Now the same thing can be said for random
variables. So suppose we have two random
变量X和Y。它们从集合V中取值。然后我们设这些随机
variables x and y. They take values in
some set v. Then we say that these random
变量是独立的，如果X=a和Y=b的概率
variables are independent if the
probability that x = a, and y = b is equal
等于这两个概率的乘积，基本上就是说，即使
to the product of these two probabilities.
Basically what this means is, even if you
你知道X=a的概率，你也不知道Y的值是多少。
know that x = a, that tells you nothing
about the value of y. Okay, that, that's
这意味着乘法需要知道所有A和B
what this multiplication means And again
this needs to hold for all A and B in the
在这些随机变量的取值空间，如果你之前看过的话
space of values of these random variables
So, just again to job your memory If
再加深一下印象。举个很简单的例子，我们看到这有一个
you've seen this before, a very quick
example. Suppose we look at the, set of,
两比特串的集合，00,01,10,11，
of two bit strings So, zero, zero, zero,
one, one zero and, one, one And suppose we
我们从这个集合中随机选取一个。我们随机选取这四个元素中任一个元素
choose a random, from this set. Okay so we
randomly choose one of these four elements
的概率相等。现在让我们定义两个随机变量。
with equal probability. Now let's define
two random variables. X is gonna be the
X是生成的最低有效位 即lsb(r)，Y是生成的最高有效位 即msb（r）。
least significant bit that was generated,
and Y is gonna be the most significant bit
然后我任命，随机变量X和Y是相互独立的。
generated. So I claim that, these random
variables, x and y, are independent of one
从四个元素中无差别选择r最直观的方法
another. And the way to see that
intuitively, is to realize that choosing r
就和抛两次硬币一样，公平的硬币两次
uniformly, from the set of four elements
is basically the same as flipping a coin
第一位对应第一次抛的结果和
An unbiased coin twice. The first bit
corresponds to the outcome of the first
第二位对应第二次抛的结果
flip and the second bit corresponds to the
outcome of the second flip And of course
当然有四种可能的结果。所有的四种结果
there are four possible outcomes. All four
outcomes are equally likely which is why
都等概率出现在这些两比特串中，现在我们的变量X和Y，
we get the uniform distributions over two
bit strings Now our variables X and Y. Y
Y是独立的，如果我告诉你抛一次的结果
the independents Basically if I tell you
result of the first flip namely I tell you
就是r，就相当于我告诉了你硬币落下来是正面还是反面
the lest signify bit of R So I tell you
how the first coin you know whether it
而第二次抛的结果什么都没有告诉你
fell on its head or fell on its tails.
That tells you nothing about the result of
这就是你的直觉，你可能期望这些随机
the second flip. Which is why intuitively,
you might, you might expect these random
变量是相互独立的，而实际上我们需要证明它。
variables to be independent of one
another. But formally, we would have to
所有的0 1对，X=0,Y=0,X=1,Y=1,的概率
prove that, for, all 01 pairs, the
probability of, x=0 and y=0, x=1, y=1, and
这些概率相乘。让我们先做其中的一个。
so on. These probabilities multiply. Let's
just do it for one of these pairs. So
看一下X=0和Y=0的概率。
let's look at the probability that x is =
to zero, and y is = to zero. Well, you see
你看X=0同时Y=0的概率应该是
that the probability that x is equal to
zero and y is equal to zero is basically
r=00的概率，然而r=00的概率是多少？
the probability that r is equal to zero,
zero And what's the probability that r is
通过均匀分布，这基本上等于四分之一
equal to zero, zero? Well, by the uniform
distribution, that's basically equal to
在这种情况下集合中的一个元素的概率就是1/4
one-fourth. What it's one over side of the
set which is one fourth in this case And
事实上这些可能的证明
well low and behold that's in fact these
probably provability multiply Because
因为再乘上了X=0的概率，即lsb（r=0）的概率
again the probability that X is equal to
zero. The probability that lest signify
这可能正是二分之一
bit of R is equal to zero. This
provability is exactly one half because
因为有两个元素他们的lsb等于零
there is exactly two elements that have
their, lest signify bit equals to zero.
四个元素证明了一半，同样的
Two out of four elements gives you a
provability of one half And similarly the
Y=0的概率也是二分之一。
probability that Y is equal to zero is
also one half so in fact the provability
我告诉你这个独立性的概念
multiplies. Okay, so that's, this concept
of independence And the reason I wanted to
是因为我们将要看一个异或重要的性质
show you that is because we're gonna look
at an, an important property of XOR that
我们将重复使用它。所以在我们讨论异或之前，让我
we're gonna use again and again. So before
we talk about XOR, let me just do a very
很快复习一下关于异或是什么。两位异或是指两个
quick review of what XOR is. So, of
course, XOR of two bits means the addition
比特相加再模2。确保每个人都在同一页上。
of those bits, modular two. So just too
kind of, make sure everybody's on the same
如果我们有两位，00,01,10,11，他们的真值表
page If we have two bits, so 0001, ten and
eleven. Their XOR or the truth table of
异或就是相加再模2。正如你所看到的，1+1=2
the XOR is basically just the addition
modular two. As you can see, one+1 is= to
再模2，就等于0.所以这就是异或的真值表
two, modular two. That's=to zero. So this
is the truth table for [inaudible] XOR And
我总是想通过圈的外加里来表示异或，
I'm always going to denote XOR by the
circle with a + inside And then when I
然后当我想异或比特串时，就按位进行相加再模2的操作
wanna apply XOR to bit strings, I apply
the, addition modular two operation,
例如，这两个字符串异或为110，
bitwise. So, for example, the XOR of these
two strings would be, 110, and I guess
我想让你填写剩下异或的结果，只是为了确保我们都在
I'll let you fill out the rest of the
XORs, just to make sure we're all on the
同一页上。它的结果为1,1,0,1，现在，我们
same page. So of course is comes out to
one, one zero one. Now, we're gonna be
会做在这堂课上做很多异或。事实上，有一个经典的笑话是
doing a lot of XORing in this class. In
fact, there's a classical joke that the
有的人认为译解密码者只是把事物异或在一起，但我想
only think cryptographers know how to do
is just XOR things together But I want to
向你解释为什么我们在密码学中看到如此频繁的异或。基本上，异或
explain to you why we see XOR so
frequently in cryptography. Basically, XOR
有一个很重要的性质，这性质是，假设有一个
has a very important property, and the
property is the following. Suppose we have
随机变量Y，任意分布在0,1区间上，所以我们
a random variable y. That's distributed
arbitrarily over 01 to the n. So we know
对Y的分布一无所知。但现在，假设我们有一个独立的随机
nothing about the distribution of y But
now, suppose we have an independent random
变量也均匀分布在0,1区间之上， 且X是均匀分布的很重要。
variable that happens to be uniformly
distributed also over 01 to the n. So it's
n对于Y是独立的。现在让我们来定义
very important that x is uniform. N's
independent of y. So now let's define the
随机变量X和Y的异或，我认为无论
random variable which is the XOR of x and
y. Then I claim that no matter what
Y怎么开始分布，Z总是均匀分布的随机变量。
distribution y started with, this z is
always going to be a uniform, random
换句话说，如果拿一个任意不均匀分布
variable. So in other words if I take an
arbitrarily malicious distribution and I
与一个独立均匀分布的随机变量异或最终得到的是一个均匀分布的
XOR with independent uniform random
variable what I end up with is a uniform
随机变量。这又是一个很好的性质
random variable. Okay and this again is
kind of a key property that makes x or
对密码学很有用。所以这是一个需要证明的非常简单的因素
very useful for crypto. So this is
actually a very simple factor to prove,
我们只需要去证明它，我们只需证明一点，n=1.
let's just go ahead and do it, let's just
prove it for one bit so for n = one. Okay,
我们证明它的方式是写出各种随机变量的
so the way we'll do it is we'll basically
write out the probability distributions
概率分布。所以我们会看到，对于随机变量Y，
for the various random variables. So let's
see, for the random variable y. Well, the
随机变量可以是0或1，并且那个P0是Y=0的概率，
random variable can be either zero or one.
And let's say that P0 is the probability
P1是Y=1的概率。
that it's = to zero, and P1 is the
probability that it's =to one. Okay, so
那就是我们的一个表格。同样的，我们会有一个变量X的表格。
that's one of our tables. Similarly, we're
gonna have a table for the variable x.
变量X的表格就相对容易些，X是一个均匀分布的随机变量。
Well, the variable x is much easier.
That's a uniform random variable. So the
X=0的概率就是二分之一，X=1的概率也是
probability that it's=to zero is exactly
one half The probability that's it's=to
二分之一。现在，让我们写出来联合分布概率。
one is also exactly one half. Now, let's
write out the probabilities for the join
换句话说，让我们先看看那不同的概率，
di stribution. In, in other words, let's
see what the probability, is for the
Y和X是联合分布概率。即Y为,0，
various, joint values of y and x. In other
words, how likely is, it that y is zero,
X为0。Y为0，X为1.Y为1，X为0，还有1 1
and x is zero. Y is zero, and x is one. Y
is one and x is zero, and eleven. Well, so
所以我们要做的是，因为我们假设的变量是独立的，
what we do is, basically, because we
assume the variables are independent, all
我们要做的就是把概率相乘。所以，Y等于0的概率
we have to do is multiply the
probabilities. So The probability that y
是P0，X等于0的概率是二分之一。
is equal to zero is p zero. Probability
that x is equal to zero is one-half. So
我们得到00是P0/2，同样的
the proximity that, we get 00 as exactly p
zero over two. Similarly for zero one
得到01是P0/2，得到10是P1/2,得到11
we'll get p zero over two, for one zero
we'll get p one over two And for 1-1,
是P1/2，Y=1和X=1的概率
again, the probability that y is=to one,
and x is=to one, Well, that's P1  the
是P1/2.
probability that x is=to one, which is a
half, so it's P1 over two. Okay? So those
所以这些就是X和Y各种选择可能性的四个概率。
are the four, probabilities for the
various options for x and y. So now, let's
让我们来分析一下，Z=0的概率是多少？Z=0的概率
analyze, what is the probability that z is
equal to zero? Well, the probability that
基本上相同的概率是，让我们这样写，
z is=to zero is basically the same as the
probability that, let's write it this way,
（X,Y）=(0,0)或（X,Y）=(1,1),这些都是Z=0可能出现的两种情况。
xy. Is=to 00. Or xy is=to, eleven. Those
are the two possible cases that z is=to
因为Z是X和Y的异或，这些事件是不相交的，所以，
zero Because z is the XOR of x and y. Now,
these events are disjoint, so, this
这个表达式可以写成上述两个表达式的和。
expression can simply be written as the
sum of the two expressions given above. So
基本上，这就是XY=00的概率，再加上XY=11的概率，
basically, it's the probability that xy
is=to 00, plus the probability that xy,
所以我们可以简单地在表中找一下这些概率。
is=to eleven. So now we can simply look up
these probabilities in our table. So the
所以XY=00的概率是P0/2，
probability that xy is equal to 00 is
simply p zero over two, and the
XY=11的概率是P1/2.所以我们得到
probability that xy is equal to one, one
is simply p one over two. So we get P0
P0/2+P1/2,但是我们怎么知道P0和P1呢？
over two +P1 over two But what do we kn-,
what do we know about P0 and P1? Well,
这是一个概率分布，因此，P0+P1＝１。因此，
it's a probability distribution.
Therefore, P0+P1 must =one And therefore,
这个部分一定等于一半，P0+P1=1。所以，
this fraction here must= to a half. P0+P1
is =to one. So therefore, the sum of these
两个部分的和一定等于一半，这样就完成了。基本上我们证明
two terms must = a half And we're done.
Basically, we proved that the probability
了Z=0的概率是二分之一，然而Z=1的概率
that z is = to zero. Is one half,
therefore the probability that z is equal
也是二分之一。因此，Z是一个均匀分布的随机变量
to one is also one half. Therefore z is a
unif orm random variable. So the simple
这个定理如此简单的原因是XOR在密码学上非常有用。我想告诉你
theorem is the main reason why x o is so
useful in cryptography. The last thing I
最后一件事就是关于一个叫做生日悖论的离散概率
wanna show you about discreet probability
is what's called the birthday paradox And
在这里我会说很快，因为我们以后会回来
I'm gonna do it really fast here Because
we're gonna come back later on, and talk
详细的讨论它。生日悖论就是下面
about this in more detail. So, the
birthday paradox says the following
假设我在区域U中选择n个随机变量，碰巧的是，
suppose I choose n random variables in our
universe u. Okay And it just so happens
这些变量是相互独立的，他们其实不必相同。
that these variables are independent of
one another. They actually don't have to
我们需要假设的是，他们分布的方式相同。
be uniform. All we need to assume is that
they're distributed in the same way. The
最重要的性质是他们是相互独立的。所以定理说，
most important property though is that
they're independent of one another. So the
如果你选择元素U大小的平方根，
theorem says that if you choose roughly
the square root of the size of u elements,
这里有一个1.2，没关系，但如果你选择
we're kind of this one point two here, it
doesn't really matter. But if you choose
元素U绝对值的平方根，有一个很大的概率会有
square root of the size of u elements,
then basically there's a good chance that
两个元素是相同的。换句话说，如果你把样本
there are two elements that are the same.
In other words, if you sample about square
平方根几次，那么很有可能你的两个样本不会
root a few times, then it's likely that
two of your samples. [inaudible] will be
相等。顺便指出，这个反向的E
equal to each other. And by the way, I
should point out that this inverted e,
的含义是存在。所以存在i不等于j并且ri=rj,
just means exists. So there exists in
[inaudible] I and j such that r I is equal
这是一个具体的例子，我们会看到很多次。
to r j. So here's a concrete example.
We'll actually see many, many times.
假设我们的区域由128位长度的字符串构成，
Suppose our universe consist of all
strings of length of one hundred and
所以U的大小其实是2的128次方，
twenty eight bits. So the size of you is
gigantic it's actually two to the hundred
它非常大，但是碰巧如果你从这个集合中
and twenty eight. It's a very, very large
set But it so happens if you sample say
取样取了2的64次方次，这是关于U的平方根
around two the sixty four times from the
set. This is about the square root of U
那么很有可能你的两个样本信息实际上是相同的。
then is very likely that two of your
sample messages will actually be the same.
所以为什么这叫做悖论？通常它用来描述
So why is, this called the paradox? Well,
traditionally it's described in terms of
人们的生日，所以你会认为这些样本是
people's birthdays. So you would think
that each of these samples would be
某些人的生日，所以问题是多少人需要在一起以至于
someone's birthday And so the question is
how many people need to get together so
有两个人的生日是相同的？所以，做一个简单的计算，
that there are two people that have the
same birthday? So, just as a simple cal
你会看到一年有365天，你需要大约1.2倍的
culation you can see there are 365 days in
the year, so you would need about 1.2
的365人的平方根，直到其中两人生日相同的
times the square root of 365 people until
the probability that two of them have the
概率超过一半。这个如果我没记错的话大概是24，这意味着
same birthday is more than a half. This if
I'm not mistaken is about 24, which means
如果24个随机的人呆在一间屋子里，很有可能其中会有两个人
that if 24 random people get together in a
room it's very likely that two of them
有相同的生日。这就是为什么它被称为一个悖论，因为24
will actually have the same birthday. This
is why it's called a paradox, because 24
可能是一个比你想象的要小的数字。有趣的是，人们的
supposedly is a smaller number than you
would expect. Interestingly, people's
生日其实不是均衡的分布在一年的365天，实际上
birthdays are not actually uniform across
all 365 days of the year. There's actually
更偏向于十二月。但是我认为没有必要
a bias towards December. >> But, I guess
that's not, that's not relative to the
在这里讨论这个。我想做的最后一件事是给你看
discussion here. >> The last thing I
wanted to do is just show you the birthday
更具体的生日悖论。假设我们有一个大约一百万样本的
paradox a bit more concretely. So, suppose
we have a universe of about a million
区域，那么你可以看到，当我们的取样大约1200次的时候，
samples, then you can see that when we
sample roughly 1200 times, the probability
我们有一半的概率在其中两次取样中取到了相同的元素
that we get, we sample the same number,
the same element twice is roughly half But
但是两次抽样相同数的概率其实非常快的收敛到了一。
the probability of sampling the same
number twice actually converges very
你可以看到如果我们有2200个样本，然后这些物品中
quickly to one. You can see that if we
about 2200 items, then the probability
两个取样相同的概率已经是90%，你知道，如果是3000
that two of those items are the same,
already is 90 percent and You know, 3000
的话，概率基本上是一。所以一旦超越了U大小的平方根，
then it's basically one. So this
conversion is very quickly to one as soon
这个变化非常快的收敛到一。所以我们以后会
as he goes beyond the square root of the
size of the universe. So we're gonna come
回来更详细的研究生日悖论，但我现在只想
back and study the birthday paradox in
more detail later on, but I just for now,
让你知道它是什么。所以这节就结束了，
wanted you to know what it is. So that's
the end of this segment, and then in the
在下一节我们将开始加密系统的第一个例子。
next segment we'll start with our first
example of encryption systems. [sound]